<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Kedarminster-stuff, a new piece of print, or, A remnant of Mr. Baxter's piae fravdes unravelled being an appendix to Nonconformists plea for peace impleaded / by J.B. Worcestershire.</title>
            <author>J. B. (John Browne)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1681</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 95 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 22 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A29834</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B5121</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R6607</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11611489</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11611489</idno>
            <idno type="VID">47902</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A29834)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 47902)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 484:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Kedarminster-stuff, a new piece of print, or, A remnant of Mr. Baxter's piae fravdes unravelled being an appendix to Nonconformists plea for peace impleaded / by J.B. Worcestershire.</title>
                  <author>J. B. (John Browne)</author>
                  <author>Long, Thomas, 1621-1707. Non-conformists plea for peace impleaded.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>41 p. ;  19 cm. </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Randal Taylor,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1681.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Baxter, Richard, 1615-1691. --  Nonconformists plea for peace.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:47902:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:47902:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>KEDARMINSTER</hi>-Stuff. A new PIECE of Print: OR, A REMNANT OF Mr. BAXTER'S <hi>PIÆ FRA<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>DES</hi> UNRAVELLED.</p>
            <p>BEING AN APPENDIX TO <hi>Nonconformiſts Plea for Peace</hi> IMPLEADED.</p>
            <p>By <hi>J. B. Worceſterſhire.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>If I ſhould zealouſly preſs my Judgment on others, and ſeek to make a Party for it, and diſturb the Peace of the Church, and ſeparate from my Brethren, I ſhould fear leſt I ſhould prove a Fire-brand in Hell for being ſuch a Fire-brand in the Church. I charge you therefore, if God ſhould give me up to any factious Church-rending courſe, that you forſake me, and follow me not a ſtep.
<bibl>
                  <hi>See</hi> Baxter<hi>'s</hi> Saints Reſt, <hi>Epiſt. Dedic. to the People of</hi> Kedarminſter, <hi>p. 8, 9.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Randal Taylor</hi> neer Stationers-hall. 1681.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:47902:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:47902:2"/>
            <head>A REMNANT OF Mr. BAXTER'S <hi>PIÆ FRA<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>DES</hi> UNRAVELLED.</head>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. I.</hi> Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>'s Title-page.</head>
               <p>THere's a Book of late extant called <hi>[Nonconfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſts Plea for Peace:]</hi> 'Tis called a <hi>[Plea]</hi> though it be indeed meer Magiſterial dictating above what any Metropolitan would arrogate or pretend to; and is apparently more like a Plot than a Plea, meerly to diſturb the Churches Peace, and embroil the Nation.</p>
               <p>'Tis called a Plea for <hi>[Peace],</hi> though it be indeed for Schiſm; and no more a Plea for Peace, than the Author's fighting againſt the King was a making Peace with him. See who will, how well 'tis fitted to alienate the minds of Miniſters and People, to ſeduce the Weak, and to confirm the Factious, to exaſperate Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours, and poſſeſs the minds of men with hateful and rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lious thoughts againſt their Government, to diſturb the Peace of Church and State, and to lay the Grounds of a laſting Separa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and he ſhall find that 'tis more likely to ſet three King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:47902:3"/>
in a Flame, than to ſettle Peace in one; it being certain that ſuch Paper-lights as theſe Pleas for Peace, did help to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flame the Kingdom with the late Civil War: 'Tis well known they were ſuch Outcries againſt Biſhops and Ceremonies, that firſt brought in plea the Kings Prerogative; 'twas pretence to Reformation and the purity of Religion, to tenderneſs of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience and the power of Godlineſs, that brought men firſt to unjuſt. Sequeſtering and wreſting away Eſtates, then to plun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering and cutting of Throats, and at laſt to the baniſhment and murder of Princes: In a word, to that which in times of the late Uſurpation robb'd us of our Laws, Government, and Peace, tore and worried our Church and State, making it a prey to Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny and Sacriledge, which ſtain'd the Proteſtant Religion with Royal Bloudſhed, and cover'd Fields with the Carcaſſes of many thouſand Chriſtians. I ſay, that which did this, was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence to Reformation and purity of Religion, the Bloud-thirſty Zeal of thoſe Puritans who (as Biſhop <hi>Bancroft</hi> foretold) would never give over their Cry for Reformation, till they had ruined us Church and State; and whatever ſpecious titles and preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces this <hi>Plea for Peace</hi> may have, 'tis certain its duct and tendency is no better: what's moſt material in it, hath had its diſquiſition by the judicious Impleader. I have now to do but with ſome of the Rubbiſh and Impertinencies of it, which that worthy Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor has paſt by as leſs worthy of his notice.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. II.</hi> Of their Separate Congregations.</head>
               <p>THE Pleader begins with Churches. His firſt underta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king is to ſhew what Churches are of Divine Inſtitution, and what not; where he endeavours, by dark Definition and nice Diviſion, to make the Church like the Multitude, many Heads, the forking it into Dichotomies meerly to amuſe the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, repreſenting to them the Notion of a Church as ſome unin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligible
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:47902:3"/>
thing, to make their Schiſm the harder to be diſcerned. He tells us, <hi>p.</hi> 8. <hi>He doubts not but that a Society of Neighbour-Chriſtians aſſociated with a Paſtor for perſonal Communion in Doctrine, Diſcipline, and Worſhip,</hi> (ſuch as their Meetings are) <hi>is of Divine Inſtitution.</hi> His 16th and 17th Sections are to the ſame purpoſe: which I have found his Followers to take for proof, that their Congregations are true Churches, and of Divine In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution. But I doubt not there are thouſands of good Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians in <hi>England,</hi> that will as ſoon believe theſe Aſſemblers Heads to be truly Steeples, as thoſe Aſſemblies to be true Churches, eſpecially as now managed.</p>
               <p n="1">1. To the great contempt of thoſe more publick Aſſemblies that have the ſtamp of Authority both from God and man, and which are of that which is the onely Church National that ever was reformed from Popery by a Law, and not out of Huddles and Tumults, as <hi>Geneva</hi> and moſt of the Reformed Churches be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond Sea were; which Reformed Church or Churches in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> as the firſt Reformers planted with their Sweat, ſo their Succeſſours watered with their Bloud, and particularly thoſe Martyrs <hi>Cranmer, Ridley,</hi> and others, that were the firſt Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pilers of the Common-prayer.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Their Antichurches are kept up to the begetting of thoſe Schiſms and Diviſions, which the beſt of Chriſtians in Primitive times have accounted as bad as Hereſie; as <hi>Chryſoſt. Epiſt. ad Eph. Edit. ſecund.</hi> p. 823. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>To divide the Church</hi> (ſays he) <hi>is no leſs evil [or ſinful] than to fall into Hereſie.</hi> And <hi>Aug. Ep. contra Parmen. l.</hi> 2. 2. <hi>Vix crimen aliquod,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>There is ſcarce any thing ſo bad as Schiſm; not Idolatry,</hi> ſaid <hi>Dyoniſ. ap. Euſeb. l.</hi> 6. <hi>Not Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge,</hi> ſaid <hi>Optatus, l.</hi> 1. <hi>'Tis <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, the original of Evils,</hi> ſaid <hi>Ignatius, Ep. ad Smyr.</hi> Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> ſays (<hi>Plea,</hi> p. 3.) <hi>Indeed could they find out the Schiſmatick, he hopes he would be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned of all.</hi> But what Quaker, Papiſt, or Schiſmatick who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever could not ſay as much? <hi>And if they knew indeed what Schiſm is</hi> (ſays he, <hi>p.</hi> 3.) <hi>they would avoid it.</hi> As though all thoſe moſt learned and beſt of men in their Ages, <hi>Ignatius, Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prian,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:47902:4"/>
Auguſtine,</hi> and others that wrote ſo much againſt Schiſm, knew not what Schiſm is, but wrote againſt they knew not what; or as though ſo great a Polygraphus as Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> after ſo many years dabling in their Writings, could not find out the definition of Schiſm. But,</p>
               <p n="3">3. God never inſtituted Churches to be kept up in diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to thoſe Chriſtian Magiſtrates which he commands us to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey upon pain of damnation, <hi>i. e.</hi> eternal damnation, as Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> expounds it, <hi>H. Commonwealth,</hi> p. 352. telling us fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>Theſ.</hi> 319. <hi>That diſobedience to our Rulers, is in Miniſters</hi> (ſays he) <hi>double treaſon and wickedneſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. In his ſame <hi>H. Commonwealth, Theſ.</hi> 240. he teacheth, <hi>That 'tis neceſſary to the Churches peace, that no private Congregations may be gathered, or Antichurches erected, without approbation and toleration from the Magiſtrate.</hi> [Where he means plain enough, all Congregations ſeparate or diſtinct from the Pariſh-Churches, as theirs now are.] Adding in the ſame page, <hi>That if private Aſſemblies be permitted unlimitedly, then</hi> 1. <hi>it will be impoſſible to reſtrain Hereſie, Infidelity, or Impiety; yea,</hi> 2. <hi>they may meet</hi> (ſaith Mr. <hi>Baxter) to plot againſt the Magiſtrate: And no Aſſemblies whatever,</hi> ſays he, [meaning beſide thoſe of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh-Church] <hi>are to be allowed by the Magiſtrate.</hi> Again, <hi>Theſ.</hi> 263, (ſaith he) <hi>If Magiſtrates forbid Miniſters to preach or exerciſe the reſt of their Office in their Dominions, they are to be obeyed.</hi> For which he inſtances in <hi>David, Solomon,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Kings taking down and ſetting up Prieſts, and ordering the Officers of the Houſe of God. And what he ſays in his <hi>Plea,</hi> p. 218. <hi>[That where there is no neceſſity of their preaching, Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conformiſts ſhould forbear it,]</hi> condemns the practice of moſt Nonconformiſts in <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. 'Tis a little regardable, that many of theſe Antichurches are kept up by thoſe very perſons who blew the Trumpets of Rebellion in XLIII, and were the moſt active Pulpiteers in ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting forward the late Civil War, and after that the Regicide; which will be made evident in the ninth Section following: And that theſe Meetings are all kept up by thoſe who look upon
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:47902:4"/>
themſelves as bound by Oath (the <hi>Solemn League and Covenant</hi>) to endeavour all the days of their lives the extirpation of Church-government by Biſhops, Deans, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> i.e. to endeavour the Overthrow of that Government in the Church which is by Law eſtabliſht; and ſo to act over again the Tragedies of Civil War, when opportunity and power ſhall give them leave.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. III.</hi> Of Biſhops.</head>
               <p>THe Pleader comes next to Biſhops, and tells us, <hi>p.</hi> 6. 13, 14, 15. <hi>That in Scripture times a Biſhop had but one fixed Society, one Church or worſhipping Aſſembly, under him; and that the greatest defenders of Prelacy have affirmed, that Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches Provincial, Patriarchal, National,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>are but of Humane Inſtitution. Anſw.</hi> So have the greateſt defenders of Noncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity affirmed Churches Congregational, Claſſical, and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, as well as Dioceſan, Provincial, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to be of Humane In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution onely. <hi>The ordering of ſuch diſtinction of Churches, are left</hi> (ſaith Mr. <hi>Tombs, Theodul.</hi> p. 21.) <hi>to divine Providence and humane Prudence.</hi> Among thoſe great defenders of Prelacy he mentions none but Dr. <hi>Hammond,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dr.</hi> Ham. <hi>Annot. on</hi> Acts 11.6. <hi>which Mr.</hi> B. <hi>miſtakes for</hi> Acts 11.30.</note> and that moſt falſly and injuriouſly, thus: [<hi>That though this Title <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> hath been extended to a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Order in the Church, and is now onely in uſe for them under the name of</hi> Presbyters, <hi>yet in Scripture-time it belonged principally, if not onely, to Biſhops; there being no E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence that any of that ſecond Order were then inſtituted, though ſoon after there were ſuch inſtituted in all Churches.</hi>] From which words the Pleader infers two things: 1. That the Office of a Presbyter that was no Biſhop, was not in being in Scripture-times. 2. That no Biſhop had more than one worſhipping Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly at once. To the firſt, <hi>Anſw.</hi> The Doctor in the next page renders this reaſon for it, <hi>That while there was no multitude of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:47902:5"/>
Chriſtians, there were found none among them that were fit to be conſtituted Presbyters (in our uſe of the word;) and therefore contented themſelves with a Biſhop onely, and a Deacon or Deacons to aſſist him; there being</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>then ſo ſmall ſtore out of which to take more, and ſo ſmall need of ordaining more: Inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mating that when the number of Chriſtians encreaſed, and there was need of ordaining more, that Order ſhould be ſet up in the Church,</hi> as it was ſoon after. So that his firſt concluſion from the Doctor's words, is very falſly inferr'd.</p>
               <p>The other thing that he infers from them is, That a Biſhop had but one Church, or one Worſhipping Aſſembly at once. <hi>Anſw.</hi> Of which there is not one ſyllable in the Doctor's words; and how far it is from his meaning and opinion, will appear to any that will but turn over his <hi>Annotations</hi> to the page prelimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary to <hi>Titus;</hi> where, from <hi>Euſebius,</hi> he affirms <hi>Titus</hi> to have been Biſhop of the Churches of <hi>Crete;</hi> and from St. <hi>Chryſoſtom,</hi> that <hi>Titus</hi> had committed to him <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, an intire Iſland. So his <hi>Annotations</hi> on <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.3.15. and other places, ſhew how groſly he miſcites the Doctor, and how falſly he aſſerts from him, That Epiſcopal Churches in Scripture-times were but ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle Congregations. And 'tis ſtrange that Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> ſhould ſay that he knows no proof ever produced of Gods inſtituting Churches Provincial, Patriarchal, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſince he himſelf hath produced ſuch full and ſolid proof of it, and that but lately, as in his <hi>Chriſtian Directions,</hi> part 7. p. 127. And <hi>N.</hi> 4. having proved the particular Orders of Presbyters and Deacons, he tells us, <hi>That beſides thoſe in the univerſal Church in the Apoſtles days, there were many general Officers under Christ, that had the care of governing and overſeeing Churches up and down, and were fixed by ſtated Relation to none.</hi> Which ſhews, that beſide the fixed Paſtors and Deacons of every Church Congregational or Parochial, there was in the Apoſtles times a larger Epiſcopacy in Gods Church, and more general Officers and Overſeers to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide and viſit the Churches, like Colonels and chief Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders in an Army, Officers different from the Captains and ſtated Officers of every ſingle Company. Thus Mr. <hi>Baxter;</hi> and yet
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:47902:5"/>
now he never ſaw proof produced of Churches Provincial, Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarchal, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> divine inſtitution. It hath been proved <hi>ex abundanti</hi> by Biſhop <hi>Hall</hi> and others, particularly Dr. <hi>Stilling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fleet</hi>'s <hi>[<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nreaſonableneſs of Separation,]</hi> that Epiſcopacy is founded on no other than Scripture, Reaſon, Apoſtolick pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice, and Antiquity: To which I adde but this, That the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles and Diſciples were diſtinct Orders of Church-Officers, as is evident from that of <hi>Judas</hi>'s forfeiting his Biſhoprick, and <hi>Matthias</hi> (according to the prediction of the Pſalm) taking it up; who being by lot declared to be his Succeſſour, was ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly advanced from the lower Order of Diſcipleſhip to that higher one of being an Apoſtle. According to which the Ancients uſed to compare the Epiſcopal Office to that of the Apoſtles, and the Presbyters Office to that of the Seventy, as Officers employed by and under Biſhops.</p>
               <p>And this name <hi>[Apoſtle]</hi> being at laſt thought too ſacred, as being fit onely for ſuch as had ſeen the Lord, and were (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the import of the word) immediately ſent by him; therefore in the early times of Primitive Chriſtianity this name Apoſtle was laid aſide, and that of Biſhop uſed in its ſtead; im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying the ſame duty and dignity, though not of perſon, yet of place, as that of Apoſtle: So that what the Apoſtles were in Chriſt's own time, that are Biſhops ever ſince; and what Rank the Seventy had in the Church in Chriſt's time, the ſame and no other our Miniſters have now.</p>
               <p>As for that trite one, of the names of <hi>Biſhop</hi> and <hi>Presbyter</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing applied to the ſame perſons, it doth no more argue every Presbyter to be a Biſhop, than the King's being a Gentleman argues every Gentleman to be a King: For admit the names were uſed in common to both, yet where do we finde that the powers are exerciſed in common alſo? That the Presbyter as well as Biſhop, has <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the power of ordaining, infli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting Church-cenſures?<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Conc. Nic.</hi> c. 5. <hi>Conc. Ant.</hi> c. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The Councils of <hi>Nice</hi> and <hi>Antioch</hi> expreſſing a manifeſt diſtinction be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Biſhops and Presbyters, do declare the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciplinary proceedings of Church-cenſures to be under the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:47902:6"/>
ordering, and not the Presbyters. But in this I am pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented by that late excellent Treatiſe <hi>[The <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nreaſonableneſs of Separation;]</hi> onely let me obſerve Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>'s Argument againſt Epiſcopacy, <hi>Plea,</hi> p. 17. Having worded it thus, <hi>That Biſhops cannot morally beget the Species of Presbyters;</hi> he argues, <hi>If Eccleſiaſtical Generation imitate Natural, then Biſhops would beget but their like; men beget men, Phyſicians make Phyſicians, and ſo</hi> (ſays he) <hi>Biſhops may beget Biſhops. Anſw.</hi> As though Biſhops ſhould be conſecrated in their Mothers womb, and Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters be ordained ſuch before they were born; and as though they could not be Biſhops or Presbyters <hi>jure divino,</hi> unleſs they were born ſuch. This is (I think) the true import and force of his Argument; not much unlike to that of his Scotch-brother, who reading in <hi>Geneſis</hi> the Hiſtory of the Creation, concludes thus: <hi>Here's not a word of Biſhops of all that God made, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Biſhops are not</hi> Jure divino.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>The unchurching of</hi> Tim. <hi>and</hi> Tit. p. 1, 2, 3.</note>
                  <hi>Ejuſdem Farinae</hi> is that of Brother <hi>Prynn,</hi> who concludes <hi>Timothy</hi> to be no Biſhop, 1. Becauſe St. <hi>Paul</hi> and St. <hi>Luke,</hi> who were acquainted with him, never called him Biſhop: 2. Becauſe he was St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Aſſociate and Fellow-traveller: 3. Becauſe St. <hi>Paul</hi> calls him a Miniſter of God: 4. Becauſe he was a young man. And I doubt not but Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>'s late Book againſt Epiſcopacy will appear altogether as futile and doubty, when it has had its due diſquiſition.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. IV.</hi> Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>'s Character of Biſhops.</head>
               <p>FRom Arguments, the Pleader proceeds to down-right reviling and railing Accuſations, ſtiling the Biſhops [<hi>Plea,</hi> 2 <hi>part, p.</hi> 153. 160.] <hi>Proud Diotrepheſes, and that it is the lordly, proud, and impatient ſpirits of the Paſtors of the Church, that are the great diſturbers and dividers of it;</hi> maliciouſly hinting, 2 <hi>Plea,</hi>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:47902:6"/>
p. 174, 175. <hi>That there are ſome of our Biſhops that ſcarce believe that there is a God, or a Life to come.</hi> And in his Book of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, <hi>p.</hi> 122. he calls them, <hi>The Military Inſtruments of the Devil.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Concerning the latter of theſe, I ſhall onely ſay to the Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der as <hi>Michael</hi> ſaid to the Devil, <hi>The Lord rebuke thee,</hi> Jude 9. though the Apoſtle in the foregoing verſe calls them, <hi>Filthy dreamers that deſpiſe Dominion, and ſpeak evil of Dignities:</hi> he calls them, <hi>Raging waves of the ſea foaming out their own ſhame,</hi> v. 13. <hi>murmurers and complainers, whoſe mouths ſpeak ſwelling words,</hi> v. 16. <hi>even they who ſeparate themſelves,</hi> v. 19. As to the former part of his Railery, 'tis ſtrange that he ſhould call Biſhops proud <hi>Diotrepheſes,</hi> ſince according to that charge of St. <hi>John</hi> againſt <hi>Diotrephes,</hi> which he alludes to, <hi>Joh.</hi> 9. none can be called ſuch but they who refuſe the Authority of Biſhops, prating againſt them maliciouſlly; which was that St. <hi>John</hi> bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med <hi>Diotrephes</hi> for, in his loving to have the preheminence. But who are more likely the proud <hi>Diotrephes</hi>'s, they who teach and practiſe Obedience to their Rulers, according to Gods Word, or they who magiſterially ſet up their own Domination, Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and Will, as the Rule of Order, Unity, and Peace? [though in ſinful oppoſition to their Rulers,] Princely preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing to all Chriſtian Churches the true and onely terms of Concord [as the Pleader in his <hi>Plea's</hi> and other Books hath done.] Who but a Pope or Scotch-<hi>Archegus</hi> could have di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctated concerning the killing and depoſing of Kings, as Mr. <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xter</hi> has done in his <hi>H. Commonw. Theſ.</hi> 358. compared with 368. <hi>If the King</hi> (ſays he) <hi>raiſe War againſt the Parliament upon their declaration of the dangers of the Commonwealth, in that caſe the people may not onely reſist him</hi> [i. e. <hi>fight against and kill him if they can] but alſo</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>he ceaſes to be King.</hi> Nay, let him ſtrain the very Papal Tyranny to what pitch of Inſolence and Impoſition he pleaſes, there are Presbyterian Claims and Preſidents will equal it. Witneſs that of their Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren in <hi>Scotland,</hi> in and ſince King <hi>James</hi>'s time, [whoſe Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline they would have had in <hi>England;</hi>] they vindicated to
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:47902:7"/>
themſelves and their Conſiſtory a ſoveraign, univerſal, and inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendent power in all things ſpiritual: They had not onely the Directive, but Legiſlative Power alſo; and all temporal things <hi>in ordine ad Spiritualia</hi> came within the verge of their Scepter; all Soveraign power had onely the Executive power of doing as they commanded, and was bound to preſerve by its Power and Arms, their ſacred Priviledges and Soveraignty: Whatever Laws enacted by King and Parliament they conceived to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Laws of Chriſt, [<hi>i. e.</hi> Preſbytery in chief] the Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterian Miniſters had power to repeal, and to diſcharge the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects from obeying. They might decree Laws of their own, not onely contrary to, but deſtructive of the Laws of the Land. The King was bound to keep their Laws, and put them in execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and if neither he nor his Council would do it, the Nobles and Commons, nay every individual perſon, was bound to do it at their direction: as may be ſeen in <hi>Presbytery diſplayed, A.</hi> Biſhop <hi>Bromhall</hi> and others. This is that Preſbytery which was in <hi>Scotland,</hi> and which Nonconformiſts would have had in <hi>England.</hi> What's there in Epiſcopal Juriſdiction, to this Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterian Inſolence? their power of citing before their Judica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory the King and his Family, of excommunicating him in caſe of non-appearance, their ſubjecting his earthly Scepter to theirs, which they called the <hi>Scepter of Christ;</hi> in a word, his being forc'd to do whatever theſe Preſbyterian Miniſters enjoyned, was that which King <hi>James</hi> had the ſmart experience of; and therefore in the Conference at <hi>Hampton-Court,</hi> p. 79. (ſaith the King) <hi>A Scotiſh Presbytery as well agrees with Monarchy, as God and the Devil; then</hi> Jack <hi>and</hi> Tom, <hi>and</hi> Will <hi>and</hi> Dick <hi>ſhall meet, and at their pleaſure cenſure me and my Council and all my Proceedings; then</hi> Tom <hi>ſhall ſtand up and ſay, It ſhall be thus;</hi> Dick <hi>ſhall reply and ſay, It ſhall be thus: And therefore</hi> (ſays the King to Dr. <hi>Reignolds) till you find I grow puſſie and lazie, I pray you, good Doctor, let Presbytery alone; for if that be once up in</hi> England, <hi>I am ſure it will keep me in breath.</hi> The Patriarchal Preſbyters among them were honoured and at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended more like Kings or Princes, than Preſbyters or Prelates.
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:47902:7"/>
In a word, ſuch was the Domination and Lordly pride of the Nonconforming Brethren of <hi>Scotland,</hi> that 'tis certain no Biſhop or Archbiſhop in <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> or <hi>Ireland,</hi> hath uſed more Authority, or Lorded it more arrogantly, than theſe Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterian pretenders to parity.</p>
               <p>Conſult who will Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>'s Writings, and he ſhall finde that <hi>England</hi> had never ſuch an <hi>Ariſtarchus;</hi> the whole world had never ſuch a Metropolitan, except the <hi>Pope,</hi> for Magiſterial preſcribing, inſolent deſpiſing, and cenſuring even all the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Churches in the world, whoſe practices agree not with his capricious humour; is not he then a fit perſon to call the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops and Church-Governours lordly, impatient, and proud <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>otrepheſes?</hi> But 'tis no great marvel, upon this conſideration, That were people brought to a due liking of Biſhops, their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved Separation could not be kept up: As <hi>Contzen</hi> the Jeſuit obſerved in theſe words:<note place="margin">His Directions for reſtoring of Popery, <hi>l 2. c. 18.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>How eaſie is it</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>to bring the Puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans of</hi> England <hi>into Order and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity with other Proteſtants, were they but brought to a liking of Biſhops?</hi> And this railing againſt Biſhops is that Seignior <hi>Bellarini</hi> adviſed, as one way for the beſt managing of the Popiſh Intereſt in <hi>England:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">His Letter to Father <hi>Young.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Let the Biſhops</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>be ſound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly aſperſed, as factious on the one hand, as worldly and careleſs on the other; and that it were well if they were removed.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. V.</hi> Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>'s Character of the Conforming Clergie.</head>
               <p>THE Pleader having had this wrathful and malicious fling at the Biſhops, ſee how like Miniſters of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel he accoſts the inferiour Clergy, calling them craftily, <hi>Raw Youths; their preaching, a ſaying over a pedantick lifeleſs Speech; and out of the Pulpit, little differing in ſpeech or life from Carnal
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:47902:8"/>
Worldlings, or formal Hypocrites,</hi> 1 Plea, p. 87. <hi>raw, cold, dry, ſcandalous Miniſters, injudicious Novices, worldly Formaliſts and Hypocrites:</hi> p. 231. <hi>He ſuppoſes ſome guilty of Hereſie, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation, Malignity, and Wickedneſs:</hi> p. 105. <hi>And the greater part of the Miniſters of</hi> England <hi>to procure the liberty of their Miniſtry by ſin, yea groſs deliberate ſin:</hi> p. 116. <hi>Ignorant Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, unfit to be truſted with the care of Souls, for their unskil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs, unſoundneſs, notorious ſloth and negligence, and great averſneſs to a holy life,</hi> &amp;c. Juſt as the old Nonconformiſts the Donatiſts reputed St. <hi>Auſtin,</hi> calling him a ſeducer, a deceiver of Souls,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Poſſid. de vita</hi> Aug. cap. 9.</note> exclaiming againſt him publickly and pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vately, that he was a Wolf that ſhould be ſlain for the preſervation of the Flock; and all this becauſe that holy man kept and defended the Communion of the Church, which thoſe Schiſmaticks rejected. The like uſage had <hi>Baſil</hi> at <hi>Neoceſarea,</hi> and <hi>Greg. Nazianzen</hi> at <hi>Conſtantinople.</hi> And thus do the Papiſts at this day call all Hereticks beſide themſelves.</p>
               <p>But what railing Quaker, what black-mouth'd Atheiſt or Schiſmatick whatever could ſay more? Yet this is <hi>Nonconfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mists Plea for Peace.</hi> The Pleader teaches [<hi>Plea,</hi> p. 33.] That Princes ought to preſerve peace and charity among the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, and hinder Preachers from uncharitable reviling each o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: Is this ſuch reviling or no? In his Scripture-proof for <hi>Infant Church-memberſhip,</hi> he teaches, <hi>p.</hi> 148. That ſharp re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching of Miniſters is the common Character of all Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical Subverters of the Church: Is this ſharp reproaching of Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters or no? Who then are the Schiſmatical Subverters of the Church? He adds in the next words, They ſmite the Shepherds, that they might the eaſier ſcatter, [ſeparate, and divide the Sheep] who teach people to ſcatter, ſeparate, and divide: And to what elſe doth this ſmiting, ſlandering, and reviling tend? Who ſees not 'tis the Atheiſt's great endeavours to make the profeſſion of the Miniſtry it ſelf, the ground of its contempt; and the diſtinctive names of Miniſters, the very Appellatives of ſcorn? So that to call a man a Prieſt, is (with ſome) to degrade
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:47902:8"/>
him below his Servant. Is it not ſad then that ſuch an old car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping Miniſter as Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> ſhould ſo abet that rampant ſin of the times, which the <hi>Leviathan</hi>-ſinners ſo ſport in? Not to ſay what the Pleader's deſigne in it is, had any man a mind to make Schiſms in the Church, what better method could he uſe, than to vilifie the Teachers of it? None could make men Schiſmaticks by perſwading to Schiſm, ſo as people ſhould perceive it; it muſt be done eruptly, by vilifying their Teachers, and repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting them as ſuch that the people may or ought to ſeparate from. Suppoſe the Devil were incarnate and dwelt among us, I appeal to the Pleader, whether this would not be his main work and buſineſs, <hi>(viz.)</hi> to make the Miniſtry and preaching of the Goſpel ſucceſleſs to the good of Souls, And I appeal to any but the Pleader, whether any thing can be deviſed condu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing more thereto, than vilifying the Miniſters and Preachers of it, as the Pleader doth; and making them odious to the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple all he can. What people, having any ſence of Religion or the fear of God, would not ſeparate from Miniſters of ſuch black Characters as the Pleader fixes on the Conforming Clergy? I ſhall end this with thoſe words of Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> in 241 <hi>Theſ.</hi> of <hi>H. Commonw. It is neceſſary</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>to the Churches peace, that no Paſtors or Chriſtians be ſuffered in Print or Speech to rail at one another, and uſe contentious or opprobrious words:—And that tolerated Churches be not ſuffered to cast ſcorn upon the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved Churches, nor be over-buſie or publick in drawing away others to their mind.</hi> He adds, <hi>If men for foul words are bound to their behaviour, and women for ſcolding be put in the Gum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble-ſtool; there's no reaſon men ſhould be ſuffered to rail on pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of their opinions in Religion.</hi> Thus Mr. <hi>Baxter:</hi> Yet he allows himſelf ſuch railing in his opinions of Religion, that no Mother <hi>Celiers, Hobbes, White,</hi> or <hi>Whitebread,</hi> would exceed. But this is juſt that which <hi>Contzen</hi> the Jeſuit adviſed in order to the promoting of Popery in <hi>England,</hi> to vilifie the Miniſters: <hi>For</hi> (ſaith he, <hi>Cont.</hi> l. 2. c. 18.) <hi>he that ſhall read the Writings of</hi> Lutherans <hi>against</hi> Calviniſts, <hi>and</hi> Calviniſts <hi>against</hi> Lutherans [much more of Nonconformiſts againſt Conformiſts] <hi>will think
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:47902:9"/>
he reads not the Invectives of men against men, but the Furies and Roarings of Devils against Devils: And hence in time</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>the very Rulers themſelves will take occaſion to change their Religion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It was on this ſame account that <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rſin</hi> gave <hi>Flacius Illyricus</hi> this Character, <hi>[Pref. in Apol. Cat.] That he was one who for divers years, by his diſcrediting Worthy and Orthodox men, and by ſtirring up unneceſſary contentions, was a troubler of divers Conſciences and Churches all over</hi> Germany. [As I wiſh Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> be not all over <hi>England.</hi>]</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. VI.</hi> Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>'s Character of Nonconformiſts.</head>
               <p>BUT are there none of this black Character among Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conformiſts? are no raw, cold, injudicious Novices, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> among them? No, they are hinted to be <hi>clear, ſerious, holy, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent Preachers,</hi> Plea, 1. p. 87. <hi>Judicious, convincing, affectio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate Miniſters,</hi> p. 231. And in his ſecond <hi>Plea</hi> 'tis <hi>totidem verbis, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder all the Heavens of God, there's no one party of Miniſters or People more able, holy, wiſe, and faithful, than thoſe that are now ſilenced, and reproached as Puritans in his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Dominions; and that they are the glory of the Churches, and of the King and Kingdom, and ſuch as no Prince in the world is equally blest with.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus, like the people of <hi>China,</hi> they fancy themſelves to have two eyes, and almoſt all the world beſide to be blind. But,</p>
               <p n="1">1. This uncharitable boaſt doth ill become ſuch holy, ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicious, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. This is no more than what the <hi>Phariſees</hi> of old, the <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſts</hi> and <hi>Quakers</hi> of late have opinioned of themſelves: The Order of Jeſuits in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> have ſtiled themſelves the <hi>Saintly Brotherhood;</hi> and 'tis certain that many Quakers excel them in their affected Gravity, many Anabaptiſts in Piety,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:47902:9"/>
the Prelates in Learning and preaching, and ſome Jeſuits in all four. But,</p>
               <p n="3">3. Who will regard this Thraſoniſm, this boaſting humour, ſince 'tis that which the Holy Ghoſt hath ſo plainly foretold and condemn'd, <hi>That in the latter days perilous times ſhould come, when men ſhould be lovers of themſelves, boaſters, proud, falſe accuſers, fierce, deſpiſers of them that are good,</hi> traytors, <hi>heady, high-minded.—From ſuch turn away,</hi> 2 Tim. 3.2.</p>
               <p n="4">4. As for their Character of Holineſs he gives them, obſerve who will their Carriage and Converſation, and he ſhall find but few things in them excelling Conformiſts, except their looking diſdainfully, walking and talking demurely, as thoſe of their predeceſſors in the 23 <hi>Mat.</hi> 14.9 <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.26 <hi>Act.</hi> 5. boaſting and conceiting of themſelves above others; avoiding the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of ſuch as they think worſe than themſelves; of being of the ſtricteſt Sect or profeſſion in Religion; their ſtraining at a Gnat, as the Pleader doth about <hi>Chriſtmas</hi>-day, when ſuch ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mels as Perjury, Sacriledge, and Diſobedience to Magiſtrates, will down well enough; their ſtarcht Converſation, ſupercilious and contemptuous Carriage towards all that are not of their O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion in Religion, inſomuch that one that never ſaw their faces before, may diſcern them, for the moſt part, from any ſort of people in <hi>England,</hi> except Quakers onely.</p>
               <p n="5">5. As for the commendation he gives of their Ability [or Learning] however they now arrogate the reputation of it, it is not long ſince Learning was judged by ſome of them to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qualifie men for approbation to the Miniſtry; Parts and Abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties were reputed Qualities no way Miniſterial: While Friends and Faction, well-meaning and little underſtanding, have been Accompliſhments beyond Study and Univerſity; when humane Learning (as one obſerves) hath been ſcoft at as vain Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy, and the enticing words of man: and under the notion of the fooliſhneſs of preaching, the ſimplicity of the Goſpel, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Ignorance hath got the ſtamp of <hi>Jus Divinum,</hi> and natural Weakneſs has paſt for ſupernatural Grace. But,</p>
               <p n="6">6. There's none queſtions the Pleaders abilities; he's able to
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:47902:10"/>
divide the Church into <hi>Species ſemper diviſibiles,</hi> into nothing, and (as a Nonconformiſt ſaid of him) to diſtinguiſh himſelf into a Fart. How many Nonconformiſts in <hi>England</hi> beſide himſelf, could in the twenty years ſtudy he ſpeaks of, finde out ſo many feeble Exceptions as he hath done, whereby to amuſe and enſnare the Rabble in the opinion of the ſinfulneſs of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity? And there are among them (no doubt) men of great Learning and Abilities, as he ſays; but allowing for the diſpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion of number between them and Conformiſts, and 'tis certain there will be found among them more <hi>Groſſum-caputs</hi> by far, than the Church of <hi>England</hi> will own. I know one of them that (becauſe he was generally reputed one of the ableſt) I ſhall here make this mention of: In a conſiderable Company diſputing with his Pariſh-Miniſter fiercely againſt Ceremonies, and particularly kneeling, being ſufficiently baffled, roſe from his ſeat, and with eyes and hands lift up, gave God thanks that he was none of the Diſputers of this world; which was judged by his Party a ſufficient Confutation of the Adverſary, and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomination of an <hi>able</hi> man: And taking their Abilities by ſuch meaſures as theſe, they are all acknowledged (as the Pleader calls them) <hi>able</hi> men. But admit they were indeed men of better learning, preaching, and living, (as they are not;) 'tis certain, no Hereſie or Schiſm in the Church, no Sedition or Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion in the State, could be carried on but by ſuch men, who by a demure converſation and tolerable parts, are able to inflame the people with unreaſonable Zeal, to ſanctifie politick Villany, and put a varniſh of Religion on the blackeſt deſignes. Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticks had always this to ſay for themſelves; The Donatiſts and Novatians were purer than others, and therefore ſeparated from the ordinary Chriſtian-Aſſemblies; <hi>Arrius,</hi> who denied the Divinity of Chriſt, was looked upon as a man of good learning and life: but were theſe men ever the leſs Schiſmaticks for their great Learning and plauſible Converſations? no, but much worſe.</p>
               <p>As for their Preaching he ſo commends, there are no doubt many among them of great Dexterity and Skill, otherwiſe how
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:47902:10"/>
could they keep up their Separation? But 1. Are there not ſuch among Conformiſts? 2. Are there not many of the Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conformiſts much followed, who have nothing whereon to fix that Character but twang and tautology, noiſe, hum and haw, ſchreeching and bawling like <hi>Baal</hi>'s Prieſts, as though God were no neerer them than the viſible Heavens? And here let not the Pleader think that I ſpeak of all of them, or that I undervalue, much leſs deride ſerious and affectionate preaching; for I have as great a veneration for it as himſelf: and were there a real di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction between affectionate preaching, which Nonconformiſts ſo affect, and rational convincing preaching, which Conformiſts ſo excel in, I had rather hear one Sermon of the former kind, than two of the latter.</p>
               <p>As for his ſtiling Nonconformiſts <hi>the glory of the Churches, of the King and Kingdom, and ſuch Miniſters as no Prince in the world is equally blest with;</hi> I ſay but this: Then they are much mended, ſince it was uſed to be diſputed, whether the Jeſuits or Puritans were like to prove more pernicious and dangerous to the Commonwealth, where both or either of them lived. <hi>Vid. Watſon</hi>'s <hi>Quodlibet,</hi> 2 Art. 1. And ſince the Lord Keeper <hi>Puc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kering</hi> propoſed the ſame thing to the Parliament, delivering to them Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi>'s Command, <hi>That they hearken not to the ſollicitations of thoſe called Puritans, who</hi> (ſaid ſhe) <hi>do nothing but diſturb the Peace and good Repoſe of Church and Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth.</hi> And concerning the ſame perſons, Dr. <hi>John Burgeſs</hi> in his <hi>Rejoynder,</hi> p. 629. obſerves, <hi>That as under the Name of Christ, and pretence of advancing his Kingdom, Antichrist was ſet up: ſo under the name of Antichrist, and pretence of onely oppoſing him, the Kingdom of Christ may be pulled down, and in part already is</hi> (ſays he) <hi>and men ſcarcely feel or fear it.</hi> And 'tis obſerved out of Biſhop <hi>Bancroft,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The Apol. for Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops voting in Parliament, <hi>p. 73.</hi>
                  </note> that he long ſince foretold, <hi>That the Puritans would never give over their clamour for Reformation, till they had utterly ruined the whole Kingdom and Church, if they were not timely ſupprest:</hi> Adding that of <hi>Livy, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rgenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus Rempubl. fatis, Dei &amp; hominum ſalutares admonitiones ſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuntur.</hi>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:47902:11"/>
And though the Nonconformiſts are (as I really be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve) irreconcilable haters of Popery, yet if Biſhop <hi>Whitgift</hi> or Dr. <hi>Oates</hi> be to be believed, 'tis certain they contribute their endeavours to the bringing in of Popery, though they are not aware of it. The Biſhop affirms [in his Letter to the Lord Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurer, in <hi>Fuller,] That to his certain knowledge, the Diſſenters were animated to Nonconformity by the Jeſuits.</hi> And Dr. <hi>Oates</hi> in his Narrative, <hi>Item</hi> 1. <hi>That the Rebellion in</hi> Scotland <hi>of the Presbyterians against the Epiſcopal Government, was contrived by the Jeſuits;</hi> Wright, Morgan, Ireland, <hi>and others, being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed to preach under the notion of Presbyterians, and to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form the</hi> Scots <hi>of the ſad eſtate they were in by reaſon of Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal Tyranny exerciſed over them.</hi> Item 11. <hi>That the Jeſuits in</hi> Scotland <hi>had ſtirr'd up the Presbyterians there to a Rebellion.</hi> Item 43. tells us, <hi>That Meſſengers were ſent into</hi> Scotland <hi>with inſtructions to carry themſelves like Nonconformiſts, and to preach to the diſaffected</hi> Scots <hi>the neceſſity of taking up the Sword for the defence of Liberty of Conſcience.</hi> So that what the Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuits did in <hi>Scotland</hi> in carrying on the Plot, was under the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſe of Nonconformiſts. And <hi>Item</hi> 73. <hi>That there were eight thouſand Catholicks ready to riſe and joyn with the diſaffected</hi> Scots, <hi>when required by the Scotch Jeſuits ſo to do.</hi> So <hi>Item</hi> 25. 51. <hi>&amp; paſſim,</hi> Shewing, that though the Nonconformiſts mean no ſuch thing, but are really irreconcilable Enemies to Popery, yet they as really are inſtrumental to Jeſuits in bringing of it in; and it's evident that they are the avowed Enemies of the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Religion as now <hi>eſtabliſhed by Law,</hi> which the Popiſh Plot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters do ſo oppoſe and hate.<note place="margin">Key of Catholicks.</note> And Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf ſaith, <hi>That the Papiſts account that if the Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritans prevail, they ſhall make great advantage of it, their being unſetled and all in pieces, giving them footing for continual at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts; and that having their Party ſecretly among Puritans, is the way to be ſure to maintain their interest.</hi> Thus Mr. <hi>Baxter:</hi> Yet theſe Puritans are ſtiled, <hi>The glory of the Churches, of the King and Kingdom, and ſuch as no Prince in the world is equally bleſt with.</hi> But I wiſh they deſerved indeed the Character here
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:47902:11"/>
given them; for I am ſure, that the more holy, wiſe, and able judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious they are, the more quiet and peaceable they will live, and the more obedient to their Governours; eſpecially at ſuch a time as this, when Diſobedience and Diviſion [that are always dangerous] do threaten moſt perniciouſly the Church and State: and therefore the turbulent and wrathful revilers of Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters and Government, the peeviſh, cenſorious, and falſe accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers, are certainly none of theſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. VII.</hi> Nonconformiſts charging the Parliament with the burning of <hi>London.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>AMong all the dirt thrown in the face of Authority, he hath no ſuch malicious fling as that at the Parliament, charging them with their making the <hi>Oxford</hi>-Act, as that horrid and cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſin for which God inflicted that dreadful Judgment the <hi>Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of</hi> London, <hi>p.</hi> 238. And that the Biſhops may be ſure to be taken notice of, he words it thus; <hi>The Parliament and Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops:</hi> as though the Biſhops were no part of the Parliament. And all this in the greateſt capital letters, to ſignifie the noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety of it.</p>
               <p>But were Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> an unprejudiced and impartial, and not a paſſionate and ſpiteful interpreter of Providences, he might have thought of many other more crying ſins, as more probable procatarcticks to aſcribe that Judgment to. We want not ſins National [of ſo deep a tincture of Hell, and ſo complicated a ſinfulneſs as to contain in them the violation of all Laws Divine and Humane, the boldeſt tranſgreſſion of the plaineſt Rules of Duty, the down-right renouncing Chriſtianity it ſelf] to aſcribe ſuch Judgments to: As, 1. The Murder of the late King, a ſtain that like <hi>Cain</hi>'s brand, will ſtick by us as long as we are a Nation. What can we think of that Crime that doth at once (as one ſpeaks) hamſtring the State, and cut the pipes of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice;
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:47902:12"/>
wrap up all in a wilde Confuſion, and ruine whole Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of men; murder the Father of the Country, Gods Vicege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, and that in a formal way of Juſtice, thereby running Juſtice through as with her own Sword? and all this in open Rebellion, which is as the ſin of Witchcraft, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.23. <hi>i. e.</hi> diaboli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal, and ſcarce ever repented of; not onely contrary to the Rules of Scripture and the Laws of Nature, but alſo contrary to many ſacred Oaths and Promiſes, the moſt ſolemn Obligations that can be faſtened on the Conſciences of men. Such a heinous crying ſin as this, is like enough to call for Vengeance, to bring a Curſe upon the Nation, and make the Land like an <hi>Akeldama,</hi> yea a <hi>Maranatha,</hi> ſcarce to be expiated without a total Exciſion and final Extirpation. Nor is the diſtance of time between the Sin and the Judgment, any thing to the contrary: for ſuch Crim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon-daring ſins are uſually puniſht at a diſtance. It was forty years after the murder of the holy Jeſus, ere the Vengeance threatned for it came upon the Jewiſh Nation. 2. Or it might have been more religiouſly aſcribed to what Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> ſpeaks, <hi>Of the Devils ſtigmatizing the Nation with the brand of PER, and of the Lands mourning for Oaths</hi> broken: Which is probable enough. But who are the Oath-breakers? they who renounce the Solemn League and Covenant, a thing which if 'twere bin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, would make Rebellion and Perjury it ſelf matters of duty; or thoſe Miniſters in Forty three who ſent away their Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions with full diſcharge from the bonds of the the Oath of Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance to war againſt their King, by the Solemn League and Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, and after that the Engagement; a thing as contrary to the Covenant, as the Covenant was to their Oaths of Allegiance and Canonical Obedience; and after that their homaging to <hi>Cromwel</hi> in a way and manner almoſt as contrary to their En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement, as that was to any of their former Oaths: ſo that they were ſhod round with Perjury, who now ſo ſtick at one Remove. Such was the compaſs of their religious ſwallow, all Oaths could down with them, but none could hold them. No marvel then (as Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> ſaith) if for Oaths broken the Land mourns. And to aſcribe that direful Conflagration, the burning
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:47902:12"/>
of <hi>London,</hi> to ſuch crying ſins, were a far more religious inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation of Gods Providence and Judgments, than to aſcribe it to an Act of Parliament that deſigned nothing but the good of the Kingdom, the peace and ſecurity of Church and State. To which I might adde, 3. The Bloud of thoſe many Chriſtians ſhed in the Civil War; all which the very Laws of the Land make Murder: For to kill any man in War, without Authority derived from him or them that have legal power to make War, is Murder. And that they who made the War had no Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſo to do, is evident from that 25 <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. c. 2. which makes it Treaſon to levy War againſt the King in his Realm, or to be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herent to the Kings Enemies in his Realm, giving them aid or comfort in the Realm or elſewhere. Many other National and crying ſins may be named, whereto we may aptly and piouſly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe this dreadful Judgment, and not thus ſpitefully to an Act of Parliament deſigning nothing but the good of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. VIII.</hi> Nonconformiſt Perſecution.</head>
               <p>HIS Book doth abound with loud Outcries of <hi>Perſecution, the loſs of their Maintenance, the ruine of their Eſtates and Health,</hi> p. 234. He ſcatters up and down his <hi>Plea</hi> frequent complaints of <hi>Goals, Starving, Ruine, Death, bloudy Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> &amp;c. as though he were in any Turkiſh Slavery or Popiſh Inquiſition. And what doth all this tend to, but to enrage the People, and to bring an <hi>Odium</hi> on the Conforming Clergy? For Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> tells us in his Preface to <hi>Cath. Theolog. That godly people will follow their ſuffering Teachers, and that their ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings will ſtir up in the people a paſſionate Zeal, which will make the people pray for the downfal of that Clergie</hi> [Prognoſt. <hi>p.</hi> 14.] <hi>as the Enemies of God and Godlineſs; and that it will make ſome of the Nonconformiſts think</hi> [p. 20.] <hi>theſe paſſions of the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:47902:13"/>
people needful to check the fierceneſs of the Afflicters, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore will let them alone. And ſome of the more injudicious and hot-brained of the Nonconformiſts</hi> (as he ſtiles them) <hi>will put the people on, and make them believe that all Communion with Conforming Miniſters or Pariſh-Churches, is unlawful, and their forms of Worſhip ſinful and Antichriſtian; and that they are Temporizers, and betrayers of Purity, that communicate or aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble with them.</hi> Theſe and the like effects, Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> ſaith, the ſufferings of the Nonconforming Miniſters will have.</p>
               <p>Who then will wonder at their noiſe of Perſecution, or que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion their ugly meaning of crying out of it at ſuch a time as this, when they have the Liberty and Indulgence which not long ſince was all that they pretended to deſire; when the Penal Laws are like to be taken off, and a door of not onely Toleration, but Comprehenſion open; which (it is believed) will pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce no other diſcovery than this, How fond they are of their [truly ſo called] beloved Separation, notwithſtanding all their clamours of Perſecution.</p>
               <p>But how are they perſecuted? Why, 1. They vilifie and reproach their Governours at their pleaſure, who yet let them alone, and paſs it by <hi>impunè.</hi> 2. They have bound themſelves by a rebellious <hi>Covenant,</hi> to endeavour the extirpation of our Church-government; which they adhere to, and refuſe to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce, notwithſtanding its complicated ſinfulneſs; and ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare themſelves to be ſuch Enemies to their Governours and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, as want but opportunity and power to act (accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their League and Covenant) the Overthrow of it and them: for which reaſon their Governours knowing their Enmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to their Government, think them not fit to be truſted with places of Miniſterial Authority and Preferment, upon their own ſeditious and pernicious terms. And this is that the Pleader calls <hi>Perſecution, the loſs of their Maintenance, the ruine of their Eſtates,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>In the Primitive Church, when the Chriſtians dwelt among Heathens, there came a Maid from her Fathers houſe to one of the Heathen Tribunals, and without any Call to it, declared her
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:47902:13"/>
ſelf a Chriſtian, ſpit in the Judges face, and ſo provoked him to cauſe her to be executed. Will any ſay this was to ſuffer Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution? So theſe third <hi>Cato</hi>'s of the Nonconformity load their Governours with Reproaches, calling them to their faces, Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, proud, and tyrannical Thorns and Thiſtles, the military Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of the Devil, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> For all this provocation, they are ſuffered to preach openly, and to be well paid privately, to act freely, and to enjoy plenteouſly all that they deſired [not long ſince] to enjoy. Few of them but have plentiful Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance; ſome, that beſide their Contribution of thirty or forty pounds <hi>per Annum,</hi> have lodged themſelves eruptly as Chaplains to Perſons of Quality; where they are attended and honoured like any Scotch <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, ſet at the Table by my Lady, when the poor Pariſh-Curate is ſet below the Candleſtick. I know in my Country here in <hi>Worceſterſhire</hi> about ten of them, and I believe the County hath not many more, moſt of which I am well aſſured hath more for his Maintenance than ever my ſelf had from the Church, who have lived a Miniſter of it almoſt theſe eight years: Yet theſe are thoſe querulous and diſconten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Creatures, thoſe poor gentle Lambs, that are ſtill bleating out Perſecution and Tyranny.</p>
               <p>Had the Loyaliſts been but half ſo favourably uſed by Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conformiſts, during the time of their Uſurpation and Tyranny, as Nonconformiſts are now by them, they would never have been ſo ungratefully querulous: 'Tis well known how they turned almoſt all out of their Livings, that adhered to their lawful Soveraign; ſent them with their Wives and Families a begging, who durſt not proſtitute their Conſciences with down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right Perjury, and having ſworn Canonical Obedience, durſt not by a contrary Oath tranſgreſs at once the Laws of God, Nature, and Nations. They obtained that Order from a blou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy Uſurper, that every Epiſcopal Divine ſhould not onely be uncapable of a Benefice, but alſo to exerciſe any act of Miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial Function; nor yet be ſuffered to get ſome little ſubſiſtence by teaching School; no, nor at laſt to live in any Gentlemans houſe, who out of pity might take him in to keep him from
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:47902:14"/>
ſtarving. Whether this, or the preſent caſe of the Nonconfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſts, be more like Perſecution, let any but a Nonconformiſt judge. Read who will, the Principles and Practices of the Nonconformiſt Brethren in <hi>Scotland,</hi> and he ſhall find (as one obſerves) that where they have the Power, their little finger is heavier than the hand and loins of a Biſhop, or Epiſcopal Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour: The authority of their Courts Eccleſiaſtical was more tyrannically exerciſed over not onely the Bodies and Eſtates, but alſo the Souls and Conſciences of men, than ever was that of the Popiſh Inquiſition: <hi>e. g. If after a little time granted for information, any refuſe to conform and ſubſcribe to their Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Faith,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Presbytery diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>play'd, <hi>p.</hi> 39.</note> 
                  <hi>their Rule of Government, their man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Worſhip, he is forthwith excommunicate, yea though his diſſent from them be but in a Theological Tenet,</hi> [which they frequently called Hereſie;] <hi>after which Excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication, upon the remonſtrance of a Commiſſioner from the Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bytery to the Civil Judge, there is a Warrant from Supreme Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority given out to command him to conform, or within few days to be put to the Horn,</hi> i. e. <hi>to be outlawed: The tender Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience not conforming, the outlawed's Eſtate and Movables</hi> [i. e. his Chattels] <hi>becomes forfeited to the King: If within a year and a day he gives not Obedience and Conformity, his whole Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venues and Rents of immovable Goods are forfeited to the King during his life. Here the man is ſtript of all his Eſtate movable or immovable; yet this is not all, but ſtill upon Remonſtrance of the Presbytery's Commiſſioner, another Letter goes out, which they call a Letter of Caption</hi> [like that of our Writ <hi>de Excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cato capiendo] which is to ſecure his Perſon, and commit him to cloſe Priſon as a Rebel. If he skulk or hide himſelf, out goes a Writ called Letters of</hi> Intercommuning, <hi>which forbids all the Kings Subjects to commune or confer with him perſonally or by Letter, upon pain of being accounted a Rebel of the ſame guilt. And if the Church requires all this of the Civil Magiſtrate</hi> [for ſo they call the Soveraignty] <hi>he is bound to obey them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now ſay who will if this be not in many reſpects as bad as the Popiſh Inquiſition, when a man ſhall be brought to all this for
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:47902:14"/>
                  <hi>Nonconformity,</hi> though but in a Theological Tenet. What are our Penal Laws on peeviſh Diſſenters, compared with ſuch Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterian Tyranny? We deſire them but to renounce a perjuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Combination, called <hi>[Solemn League and Covenant,]</hi> an Oath taken contradictory to a former; which if it binde the Conſcience, a man may be bound in Conſcience to ſteal, rebel, murder, or any thing; he has no more to do but ſwear, and he is bound in Conſcience to do it: an Oath which ſome Noncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formiſts have called a very Neſt of Villany, and ſuch (ſaid one of them) that no perſon or people fearing God ever took. We deſire them but to ſubſcribe and conform to ſuch Church-Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline and Order as many of themſelves have acquitted from all intrinſick ſinfulneſs, and (I think I may adde) ſuch as onely can comport with the preſent Government of State. In caſe of Nonconformity hereto, the penalty is, to ſome advantageous, to all eaſie and tolerable. And what's this to Scotch Church-tyranny over Soul, Body, and Eſtate, for diſſenting but in a Theological Tenet, which the Preſbyterian Miniſters would have had brought into <hi>England;</hi> or to that Cruelty which they exerciſed on the Loyaliſts when in their uſurpt power?</p>
               <p>But to end this, let me beſpeak the Nonconformiſts in the words of the Independents to the Preſbyterians, in a thing prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted 1648, called <hi>[The Pulpit-Incendiary]</hi> directed againſt Mr. <hi>Calamy, Caſe, Cranford,</hi> and others, <hi>p.</hi> 45. the words are theſe: <hi>You complain of your miſery and bondage, ſorrows and oppreſſions, and troubles of the Church; [i. e.</hi> the Preſbyterian Church] <hi>What ails you? what troubles you? who oppreſſes you? where is the least ſhew of oppreſſion, or cauſe of complaint miniſter'd to you, except it be becauſe you are not ſuffer'd to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs your Brethren? Can you feed upon nothing but Bloud, yea, the bloud of your Brethren, that though you have every thing elſe, you ſo complain of ſorrow and oppreſſion? Is this your ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row and oppreſſion, that you cannot oppreſs?</hi> Thus the Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendent to the Preſbyterian, <hi>i. e.</hi> Nonconformiſts to one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in 48. And 'tis even ſo with Nonconformiſts ſtill. This is their Perſecution, that they cannot perſecute; this is their Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:47902:15"/>
that they are not ſuffer'd to domineer: So certain it is, that nothing but governing will ſatisfie them, let them pretend what they will.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. IX.</hi> Nonconformiſt Loyalty.</head>
               <p>HIS ſeventh <hi>Sect.</hi> from <hi>p.</hi> 120. to <hi>p.</hi> 140. gives in a Liſt of ſome few harmleſs Tranſactions relating to the late Civil War, whereby he would betray his Reader into an opinion of Nonconformiſts innocence, <hi>And that they were no promoters of the Civil War, nor had any hand in the Kings death, inſinuating that they wrote and preacht against it;</hi> (p. 130, 132.) <hi>that they were of thoſe that reſtored the King.</hi> Nor do they ſtick to tell the world, <hi>That no people in the world have better principles of Loyalty and Obedience than they.</hi> Thus will they tell the Sun 'tis midnight, and yet be believed by their credulous Followers. But this hath had its full confutation by the Impleader, who hath made their guilt evidently to appear as much notorious to be denied, as it is impious to be defended: and therefore I ſhould paſs it by. But ſeeing, 1. that notwithſtanding all that can be ſaid, the belief of their innocence in this matter gets ground daily; and 2. that their <hi>Pleas for Peace, Way of Concord, Melius In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quirendums,</hi> &amp;c. are of the ſame tendency as thoſe Paper-ſcuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fles that began the Civil War: Seeing theſe things, I think he doth a good office who at any time endeavours the undeceiving of Poſterity in ſuch a matter as this is, and gives the world what warning he can of thoſe Wolves in Sheeps-cloathing, that ſo worried Church and State into their wild and ruinating confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions; though he do no more but make more publick what is publiſhed already of thoſe ſeditious Invectives againſt the King, and Incitements to Rebellion, which the Nonconformiſts Pulpits flamed with, venting not onely from Pulpit but Preſs, their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellious Doctrines as religious Maximes, like Razors ſet with
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:47902:15"/>
oyl (ſaid one) to cut the throat of Majeſty with their ſmooth keenneſs.</p>
               <p>I begin with Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> H. Commonw. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 358. compar'd with 368. <hi>If the King</hi> (ſays he) <hi>raiſe war against the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, upon their declaration of the dangers of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth—in that caſe the King may not onely be reſiſted</hi> [i. e. fought againſt, kill'd] <hi>but he ceaſeth to be King.</hi> Yet ſpeaking of the Governours then in being, who by Rebellion and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury had uſurpt Supremacy, <hi>Pref. to H. Commonw.</hi> he ſaith, <hi>They were the best Governours in the world, and ſuch as Subjects are forbid to depoſe, on pain of damnation.</hi> In his <hi>Preface to H. Commonw.</hi> p. 23. he ſpeaks it like a Challenge to the whole world, <hi>That if any man can prove that the King was the highest Power in the time of thoſe Diviſions, and that he had power to make that War which he made,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Though St. <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith, the King is Supream.</note> 
                  <hi>he will offer his head</hi> [he means, his neck] <hi>to Juſtice as a Rebel.</hi> [So that every one taking the Oath of Allegiance and Supremacy Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> condemns for Perjury.] He tells us in <hi>H. Commonw.</hi> p. 486. <hi>That he having often ſearched his own heart whether he did lawfully engage in the War or not, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage ſo many thouſands to it, that the iſſue of all his ſearch was this—That he cannot ſee that he was miſtaken in the main, nor dares he repent of it, nor forbear doing the ſame, if it were to do again in the ſame ſtate of things.</hi> He ſays indeed in the ſame place, <hi>That if he could be convinced that he had ſinn'd in that matter, he would as gladly make publick recantation, as he would eat or drink;</hi> which he never did yet: And therefore is ſtill of the ſame mind, and would on the ſame occaſion do the ſame things, <hi>i. e.</hi> fight and encourage ſo many thouſands to fight a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the King.</p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Calamy,</hi> in a Sermon before the Houſe of Lords, on <hi>Chriſtmas</hi>-day, 1644. p. 29. <hi>That 'tis commendable to fight for Peace and Reformation against the Kings commands:</hi> p. 9. <hi>And that all that fought under the Kings Banner against the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, fought themſelves into ſlavery, and did endeavour by all bloudy means to ſubvert Religion and Liberty:</hi> p. 12. <hi>And that
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:47902:16"/>
the King that ſhould have been a Head of Gold, was an Iron Head to cruſh his own body in pieces:</hi> p. 18. <hi>That thoſe that made their peace with the King at</hi> Oxford, <hi>were the</hi> Judas's <hi>of</hi> England; <hi>and it were just with God to give them their portions with</hi> Judas: p. 13. <hi>That thoſe that engaged in this Cauſe [i. e.</hi> the War againſt the King] <hi>and the Covenant, were unjuſtly charged with Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion:</hi> p. 38. <hi>That it was Gods Cauſe, and it ſhould at last prevail.</hi> And in his Speech at <hi>Guild-hall,</hi> Oct. 6. 1643. <hi>That this Cauſe was every way ſo just and good, that if he had as many lives as he hath hairs of his head, he would be willing to ſacrifice them all in that Cauſe, i. e.</hi> the War againſt the King.</p>
               <p>So Mr. <hi>Caſe,</hi> in his Sermon before the Houſe of Commons, on <hi>Ezek.</hi> 20.25. Epiſt. Dedic. <hi>Ye [i. e.</hi> the Parliament] <hi>have overcome the Lion and the Bear, why may ye not overcome this uncircumciſed Philiſtine, who hath not ceaſed to blaſpheme the Armies of the living God? Behold HE lies groveling at your feet! what doth there remain but C<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>TTING OFF HIS HEAD?</hi> And in his Sermon on <hi>Ezra</hi> 10.2. <hi>How hath the preaching of Christ ſcorched thoſe Cathedral Prieſts, the unhallowed Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Scribes and Phariſees, and perfected their Rebellion into that unpardonable ſin against the Holy Ghost?</hi> Mr. <hi>Caſe</hi> on <hi>Dan.</hi> 11.32. before the Houſe of Commons, <hi>Curſed be he that holdeth his Sword from Bloud, that ſpares when the Lord ſays ſtrike,</hi> p. 24. <hi>that ſuffers thoſe to eſcape whom God hath appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to deſtruction.</hi> In a Sermon on <hi>Iſai.</hi> 43.4. <hi>What a ſad thing is it (my Brethren) to ſee our King in the head of an Army of</hi> Babylonians, <hi>refuſing to be called the King of</hi> England, Scotland, <hi>and</hi> Ireland, <hi>and chuſing rather to be called the King of</hi> Babylon! Again, p. 18. <hi>Prelacy and Prelatick Clergie, Prieſts and Jeſuits, Ceremonies and Service-book, were mighty Impediments in the way of Reformation, and God hath mightily pull'd them down.</hi> Preaching to a Court-Martial on 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 19.6. <hi>You know</hi> (ſays he) <hi>how the</hi> Midianites [<hi>i. e.</hi> the King and his Party] <hi>with whom you have to do, have vext you with their Wiles, and labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to obſtruct and cut us all off in our paſſage to the Land of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe; that bleſſed Reformation which the Parliament conſult for,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:47902:16"/>
Aſſemblies diſpute for, Armies fight for, and all good Chriſtians pray for; therefore do you honour God in avenging your Brethren on thoſe</hi> Midianites, <hi>in doing execution on thoſe Enemies of Christ and the Kingdom.</hi> And in his Book of the Covenant, deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in three Sermons, <hi>He that hath been a Malignant or Neutral, let him be ſo no more; for I protest against every man that after his ſtriking this ſolemn Covenant with God, ſhall dare to perſist in any of theſe mentioned Abominations; [i. e.</hi> adhering to the King, Ceremonies, <hi>&amp;c.] he is an Enemy to Christ, a Traytor to the Kingdom, a State murderer, a deſtroyer of himſelf and his Poſterity,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Herle</hi> in his Sermon before the Houſe of Commons, on 1 <hi>King.</hi> 22.22. p. 28. <hi>If the Devil can but get a Prophet to leave Gods ſervice for the Kings, he hath taken a Blue already, and is ready for as deep a Black as Hell can give him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There may be produced many thouſand inſtances of the like, ſhewing how active they were in, and how far contributing to, the late Civil War, and conſequently the Murder of the King. And thus they whoſe firſt Inſtitution made them Meſſengers of glad tidings between God and his People, have made them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves Heraulds to denounce war between Gods Vicegerent and his Subjects; and that not onely by caſting a ſlur upon the King, and repreſenting him as unworthy to be King, but by clamou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring againſt Biſhops and Ceremonies,<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Blair,</hi> Mr. <hi>Jenkins.</hi>
                  </note> as the blinde brood of Antichriſt, Popiſh traſh and trumpery, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Which ſame method is juſt now reviving; I pray God prevent the ſame ſad conſequents and effects. But notwithſtanding all this, they ſtill out-face the Sun, and ſay, [as the Pleader doth] That they preacht and wrote againſt the War and Regicidie, and that they were of thoſe who reſtored the King: But alas, when?</p>
               <q>—Galeatos ſerò duelli, poenituit.</q>
               <p>When the Independents had rode them like fools, they were
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:47902:17"/>
glad to part Stakes. 'Tis certain theſe Preſbyterians never attempted the Kings reſtoring, till they were viſibly in th<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> very jaws of the Phanaticks, that would ſuffer them to domineer no longer; but were then ſeizing on their Tithes and Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, the laſt morſel of their Spiritual Revenues: So that (as one ſaid) if the Tithe-pig had not cry'd louder in their ears than either their Conſcience or the Word of God, they had not been awakened to attempt it,</p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> objects, That it was not the Preſbyterian, but a rude conquering Army that put the King to death. <hi>Anſw.</hi> A rude conquering Army were the immediate Agents, but who impower'd them to do it? thoſe Under-parties and inferiour Sects. How broke they in upon us, but at the Schiſm and breach that Preſbyterians firſt made? This point of Noncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formiſts guilt, as to the promoting of the War and the Kings death, may be cleared from other Topicks, as the Covenant, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But <hi>hanc movere nolo Camerinam.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In aſſerting Nonconformiſt Loyalty, Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> proceeds to tell us, <hi>p.</hi> 30. <hi>That Princes and Rulers may forbid—all that preach Rebellion or Sedition, that propagate ſuch wicked Doctrine, and that they may puniſh them that do it:</hi> p. 247. <hi>And that they ſhall never be against making the ſtrictest Laws to puniſh Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conformiſts that ſhall be proved guilty of Sedition or diſloyalty,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Anſw.</hi> Not to call Nonconformiſts diſloyal or ſeditious, I leave to the Readers judgment theſe things following; which Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> in his firſt Plea ſpeaks not as his own onely, but as the ſentiment of his whole Party. He teaches, <hi>p.</hi> 226. <hi>That Paſtors preached against the will of Princes for three hundred years, and after that against the will of Chriſtian Princes.</hi> And <hi>p.</hi> 26. <hi>That God hath wrought Miracles to juſtifie thoſe that would not ceaſe preaching, when Princes, yea Chriſtian Princes have forbid them: Particularly the Biſhops of</hi> Africa, <hi>who for preaching when the King forbad them, had their tongues cut out by the Kings com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, and yet ſpake freely after their tongues were cut out.</hi> Where though he call them Chriſtian Princes, yet all that he alledges for it, proves no ſuch thing, but that thoſe Princes were
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:47902:17"/>
all <hi>Arrians,</hi> or uſurping Conquerours. Is this diſloyal and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditious or not, to argue the duty of Nonconformiſts preaching in diſobedience to Chriſtian Princes, and in ſpite of their Laws, from Miniſters diſobeying ſuch Uſurpers and <hi>Arrians</hi> as he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances in <hi>Valens, Conſtantius,</hi> &amp;c. that becauſe <hi>Athanaſius, Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſil,</hi> and <hi>Miletius</hi> preached notwithſtanding the prohibition of Arrian Princes, that therefore Nonconformiſts of <hi>England</hi> muſt, notwithſtanding the Interdict of the King? What doth this argue, unleſs the King and Clergy of <hi>England</hi> were Uſurpers that had not the power of forbidding them to preach, or <hi>Arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> that would not ſuffer any Miniſters to preach Chriſt? A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain he tells us, <hi>p.</hi> 225. <hi>That Papal <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpations, and impoſing of things unneceſſary as neceſſary to <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion and Communion, hath been the great cauſe of Schiſms throughout the Chriſtian world for this thouſand years. And</hi> p. 226. <hi>that they who ſtill obey ſuch</hi> dividing Impoſers, <hi>do continue Schiſms in the Church by encouraging the cauſes of them.</hi> Where by [dividing Impoſers] we muſt underſtand the King, Parliament, and Clergy of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land;</hi> for who elſe can he pretend to ſay impoſes upon them? And if no body impoſeth on them, why doth he clamour and complain of dividing Impoſers? What mean thoſe black Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cters he gives the conforming Clergy of <hi>England,</hi> of deliberately perjured perſons, and a hundred the like? What People fearing God would not abhor ſuch a Miniſtry, and in ſpite of all law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Authority, fight and die, do and ſuffer any thing, rather than hazard their Souls in truſting them to the care and conduct of ſuch Miniſters? Interpret who will, his meaning, in ſuggeſting it as the opinion of ſome Caſuiſts, <hi>That Humane Laws bind not, when they are not for the common good,</hi> [of which good the people muſt be judge;] Adding, <hi>That he had rather ſay, When they are notoriouſly against the Laws of Christ, and the common good;</hi> intimating the Laws of <hi>England</hi> to be ſuch: for what Laws elſe are they concern'd with? Had Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> a mind to preach Sedition, what would he ſay more? None that deſigne Sedition, will teach it openly and <hi>in terminis;</hi> that will not take: It muſt be done inſinuatingly and diſguiſedly, as— <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:47902:18"/>
Yet Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> in the name of the reſt of the Nonconformiſts, would have Princes forbid and puniſh all that propagate ſedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious and diſloyal Doctrine; and would have the ſtricteſt Laws made to puniſh any Nonconformiſts that ſhall be proved guilty of Sedition or Diſloyalty.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. X.</hi> Kneeling.</head>
               <p>ANother Scruple of the Pleaders which the Impleader hath paſt by, is kneeling at the Sacrament: And of all the ugly Pimples that fluſh in the face of Nonconformiſt Churches, there's none looks worſe than this, upon the account of that great breach that of it ſelf it makes in Church-Communion; the Word and Sacrament being the two principal materials of Church-Communion. And for this he urges nothing but the old Cant, in four particulars.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> Sitting being the Table-geſture, <hi>Sitting as men do at Meat</hi> (ſaith he, <hi>p.</hi> 150.) <hi>is certainly lawful.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> As though the Lords Supper were a common Feaſt, and the adminiſtration of it to be guided by the Rules of common Table-fellowſhip; and if ſo, why do not Diſſenters receive it with their Hats on? for that is as correſpondent to the ordinary Table-geſture as ſitting is.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> He urges the Example of Chriſt. Whereas,</p>
               <p n="1">1. 'Tis not certain what geſture Chriſt uſed: All that we read of it is,<note place="margin">Luke 22.14, 15, 20. John 21.20.</note> that he did eat the Paſſover with his Diſciples in a tricliniary geſture, which we now expreſs by ſitting: Whereas,</p>
               <p n="1">1. It was the ordinary cuſtom of the Jews to change their geſture,<note place="margin">Buxt. Syn. Judaic. <hi>cap. 13.</hi>
                  </note> even during the Paſſover it ſelf; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as the Sacrament was <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, ſays the Text, <hi>Luke</hi> 22.20. Beſide, 'tis nowhere ſaid, that Chriſt and his Diſciples continued in the Table geſture at the bleſſing of the Holy Supper.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:47902:18"/>2. There's the ſame reaſon for our imitation of Chriſt in one circumſtance as well as another; and ſo if we muſt imitate Chriſt at the Sacrament in Geſture, why not in Time and Place alſo? and ſo as Chriſt did in an upper-room after Supper, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But,</p>
               <p n="3">3. If we muſt imitate Chriſt's practice herein, we muſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive it kneeling, <hi>i. e.</hi> in conformity to the cuſtom of the Church where we live; ſo did Chriſt and his Apoſtles, they received the Paſſover in that Geſture which was then in uſe in the Jew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh Church.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> A third thing he urges againſt kneeling [which I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve is as much againſt his own knowledge] is the cuſtom of the Church Catholick, and the Canons of general Councils, particularly <hi>Nice,</hi> 1 <hi>Can.</hi> 20. that prohibiteth Adoration on a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Lords-day in the year.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Though Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> alledge this to amuſe his Follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, yet he knows,</p>
               <p n="1">1. That that ſame Council which forbad Genuflexion, did require ſtanding, and not ſitting. And,</p>
               <p n="2">2. That that injunction of the Church was onely to ſignifie their belief and joy concerning their own and Chriſt's Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, and not to continue in the Church after the Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on was ſufficiently believed; for if it were ſtill binding, we muſt receive the Sacrament ſtanding, and not ſitting or kneeling. But,</p>
               <p n="3">3. Admit that the Primitive Chriſtians did receive the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament kneeling [which they did not] yet that would not prove kneeling unlawful upon this account, becauſe the Church is not bound to obſerve always the ſame indifferent Rites and Geſtures: for though Chriſt and his Apoſtles ſate when they taught the people, <hi>Act.</hi> 16.13. yet all Miniſters are not bound thereby to the ſame Geſture.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fourthly,</hi> A fourth ſcruple he has againſt kneeling, is its ſym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolizing ſcandalouſly with idolatrous Papiſts, who ſignifie there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by Bread-worſhip or Idolatry.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> This ſame Argument is as good againſt ſitting; for that is as much a ſymbolizing with <hi>Papiſts, Arrians,</hi> and <hi>Heathens.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:47902:19"/>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Durand. rat.</hi> l. 4.</note>1. <hi>Papiſts.</hi> The Pope himſelf, at ſome Solem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Alt. Dam.</hi> c. 10.</note> receives the Euchariſt ſitting. And the Benedictine Monks the Thurſday before <hi>Eaſter,</hi> receive it ſitting.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Sitting is a ſymbolizing with <hi>Arrians.</hi> The <hi>Arrians</hi> in <hi>Poland</hi> denying the Divinity of Chriſt,<note place="margin">Syn. Craco.</note> were the firſt Authors, known to thoſe Churches, of this ſitting geſture.</p>
               <p n="3">3. 'Tis a ſymbolizing with <hi>Pagans.</hi> Sitting was the ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry geſture of Worſhip in the Romiſh Pagan Idolatry. <hi>Plutarch</hi> affirms, That the ancient Laws of their Pagan-worſhip required <hi>ut adoraturi ſedeant,</hi> that they worſhip ſitting. Now if ſym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolizing with Papiſts be a ſufficient Argument againſt kneeling, why is not ſymbolizing with Papiſts, Arrians, and Heathens, a good Argument againſt ſitting; and ſo Chriſt's inſtitution of the Sacrament made void by admitting no geſture to be lawful? Yet by this ſuperſtitious fear of ſin in kneeling, do they break Communion with us, and ſcare many wholly from the Sacrament in publick and private both; like that good Phyſician, that out of tenderneſs to his Patient, leſt he ſhould hurt himſelf by drinking, ſtole his ſilver Cup. 'Tis enough to ſhew, that this ſcruple [like the reſt] doth not ariſe from any tenderneſs of Conſcience, but peeviſhneſs and obſtinacy; that the Church of <hi>England</hi> hath ſo openly and plainly declared a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all adoration of the Sacramental Bread and Wine,<note place="margin">Rubrick after the Communion.</note> or any corporal preſence of Chriſt's natural fleſh and bloud therein. And is it not ſhameful obſtinacy when men ſhall be ſo tempted to contemn that ſacred Ordinance which the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Chriſtians ſo begg'd upon their knees! that it ſhoul'd ſo ſuperſtitiouſly be made the cauſe of Strife and Diviſion, which was intended to unite us in love to one another! That men ſhould chuſe to go to Goal rather than to the Lords Table, for fear of kneeling, and all upon ſuch feeble pretences as the beſt that the learned Pleader could produce! This ſcruple hath been ſo oft, ſo fully, and ſo convincingly confuted, that Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> (in his Book againſt <hi>Bagſhaw</hi>) tells us, That the Nonconfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſts
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:47902:19"/>
of <hi>London,</hi> upon conſult in this matter, did generally de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine to receive the Sacrament of the Pariſh-Miniſter [and kneeling.] Which ſhews that they are convinced of the law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs of it, and do act in this matter contrary to a known du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, meerly to keep up the Separation. And in his fifth <hi>Diſput. p.</hi> 411. That himſelf would kneel rather than diſturb the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches peace; intimating that himſelf doth not believe it to be ſinful, though he would have his Followers to believe ſo. I know one or more Nonconformiſts of the greateſt note in <hi>Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſterſhire,</hi> who having acknowledged the lawfulneſs of knee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, ingenuouſly declared, that they refuſed Communion with their Pariſh-Miniſter, and gave the Sacrament in houſes, meerly in compliance with the people, and for fear of loſing them; (as much as to ſay) For fear leſt their Faction ſhould return to U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion and Church-Communion, and (as Mr. <hi>Zach. Crofton</hi> ſaid) ſerve God and do their duty, leaving their Leaders to their diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembling tricks.</p>
               <p>The reſt of his Exceptions are for the moſt part ſuch as do vaniſh in the very naming of them: As,</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>That every Pariſhioner ſhould receive the Sacrament twice a year.</hi> As though every Child or Ideot were thereby obliged to it, or as though the Church meant any but perſons duly qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lified; though the<note n="*" place="margin">Mr. <hi>Cartwright.</hi>
                  </note> greateſt Nonconformiſts in Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi>'s time, and the<note n="†" place="margin">Alt. Dam.</note> greateſt in King <hi>James</hi>'s time, ſeemed to think three times a year too little, and therefore would have all who were in the Churches Communion, forc'd to receive <hi>Statis temporibus omnes adigendi,</hi> ſaid the latter; forc'd by civil puniſhment, ſaid the former.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>That all Prieſts and Deacons are to ſay dayly the Morning and Evening-prayer privately or openly, not being let by ſickneſs or ſome other urgent cauſe.</hi> Where is the Exception? or what is the evil of praying when they can awhile? for the injunction intends no more.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>He excepts against the uſe of Godfathers and Godmothers;</hi> though himſelf [in <hi>Scripture proof of Infants Baptiſm,</hi> page preliminary to his Epiſt. Dedicatory] hath proved ſufficiently,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:47902:20"/>
that the uſe of Godfathers and Godmothers is, if not Apoſtoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal, yet of greateſt antiquity in the Church, it being uſed in <hi>Hyginus</hi>'s time, who lived (as he proves from <hi>Helvicus, Paraeus, Prideaux,</hi> and others] within fourty years of St. <hi>John,</hi> and convers'd with the Diſciples and Familiars of the Apoſtles; and ſo (as he urgeth) cannot be ignorant of the practice of the Apoſtles in baptizing Infants. So that (according to Mr. <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xter</hi> himſelf) it's probable enough that the uſe of Godfathers and Godmothers is Apoſtolical. However, that it is of greateſt antiquity in the Church, himſelf hath proved, beyond the reach of ſcruple; nor are any other of his ſcruples much leſs futile. Is it not a ſhame then for thoſe Diſſenters to make ſuch pitiful Pleas for Peace and Nonconformity, to diſturb the Churches Peace, and endanger the Safety of the Kingdom, on ſuch frivo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous pretences and ſcruples, no more rational or religious than that of their Brethren in <hi>Scotland,</hi> who once ſcrupled the law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs of ſending ſealed Letters into <hi>Spain,</hi> leſt the Wax ſhould be employed in making Tapers to the Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> or other Saints, and ſo they ſhould be acceſſory to Idolatry; or than that of a <hi>Worceſterſhire</hi>-Nonconformiſt, who kill'd his Fathers Grey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hound [contrary to his Interdict and Intreaty] becauſe it was (ſaid he) a profane creature.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. XI.</hi> Now upon a due diſquiſition of theſe things, judge who will of theſe <hi>Queries</hi> following.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> 1. WHether that which Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> ſaith of Conformity, be not much more true of Nonconformity <hi>(viz.)</hi> That there is more in Mr. <hi>Tombs</hi> for Anabaptiſtry, in the late <hi>Hungarian</hi> for Polygamy, in others for Drunkenneſs, ſtealing and lying in caſes of neceſſity, than ever hath been publiſhed yet for the lawfulneſs of Nonconformity?</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:47902:20"/>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> 2. Whether the preſent ſad Separation be not kept up chiefly by this Cheat <hi>(viz.)</hi> the Peoples ſuppoſing Nonconfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſts to know Communion with our Church to be unlawful and ſinful? whereas they do believe and know the contrary; and accordingly [ſome of the learnedeſt of them] have declared publickly the innocence and lawfulneſs of our Church-Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, Liturgy, and Ceremonies, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> who yet could never be brought to ſay one word to the people of this their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> 3. Whether Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>'s taking up with ſuch frivolous Exceptions, and being guilty of ſo many groſs and palpable ſelf-contradictions in defending Nonconformity, be not ſome proof that he writes what he doth not believe, and deſignes nothing in his Writings but to amuſe the people and ſupport the Separation? and whether he could with all his Learning have deviſed any thing more, whereby to perpetuate a rigid Sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> 4. Whether their being ſo ſtudious of new Scruples, and ſo buſie at reviling Governours and Government, at ſuch a time as this, when Indulgences to them abound, when their Intereſt gets ground, when they enjoy all that liberty that once they did pretend to deſire, when there are attempts of opening the doors of Toleration and Comprehenſion to them, and when the attempters have been ſo ſcurrilouſly reproacht, and ſo abuſive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly requited for it, as that excellent perſon Dr. <hi>Stillingfleet</hi> and others have been: Whether this be not ſome ſigne that they affect Nonconformity, and are fond of their Separation, and to be ſatisfied with nothing but governing; and that it is not Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, [as King <hi>James</hi> ſaid at <hi>Hampton-Court</hi>] but Contuma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy that keeps them from conforming?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> 5. Whether their refuſing to renounce the Covenant, which Mr. <hi>Alſop</hi> calls the great Mountain in their way to Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity; whether this doth not import their belief of the obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of that diabolical Sacrament, and ſo that they look upon themſelves as bound thereby to endeavour the alteration of the Government, as ſoon as they can ſtrengthen their Party, and get
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:47902:21"/>
power and opportunity ſo to do? And whether the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment had not need to have a very watchful eye over ſuch as ſo look upon themſelves as obliged to endeavour all they can its overthrow, who have ſworn, and ſtand to their Oath, expreſly thus never to give themſelves to Neutrality or Indifferency in extirpating the Government, [as 'tis now by Law eſtabliſh'd] but will zealouſly and conſtantly continue their endeavours all the days of their lives, to extirpate the Church-government by Biſhops, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> That they will do this againſt all oppoſition, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all lets and impediments whatever, as the words of the Oath are.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> 6. Whether the Nonconformiſts would endure in the Kingdom a Party ſo combined againſt them, as they are againſt the preſent Government, had they the power that once they had?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> 7. Whether the like out-cries againſt Biſhops and Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, the like Paper-ſcuffles as theſe Pleas for Peace, were not the immediate fore-runner, and much of the cauſe of the late Civil War?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> 8. Whether all thoſe convulſive State-troubles we are in, all thoſe Fears and Jealouſies of Popery that the Nation groans under, be not truly and rightly aſcribed to thoſe Abettors of Nonconformiſt-principles, who baniſhed the D. of <hi>Y.</hi> thither where he was ſeduced to the Church of <hi>Rome?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> 9. Whether that tenderneſs of Conſcience and purity of Religion which Nonconformiſts ſo pretend to, can conſiſt with that ſchiſmatical diſturbance of the Churches Peace, that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſing Dominion, and ſpeaking evil of Dignities, that vilify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Miniſters, and diſobeying of Magiſtrates, which Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conformiſts are ſo notoriouſly guilty of, and which are as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the Word of God, as Mr. <hi>Tombs</hi>'s Anabaptiſtry, the <hi>Hungarian</hi>'s Polygamy, lying, ſtealing, drunkenneſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> 10. Whether theſe Nonconformity-ſcruples can in the judgment of right Reaſon or Religion, countervail one of thoſe many evils of thoſe diviſions of Church and State, which they occaſion? Such are,</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:47902:21"/>1. That want of Chriſtian love and tenderneſs of affection which Chriſt ſo much enforceth upon his Church and People, much unchriſtian cenſoriouſneſs, and raſh judging one another, that <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, that bitter envying and ſtrife, which St. <hi>James</hi> ſo condemns as carnal, ſenſual, deviliſh, <hi>Jam.</hi> 3.14, 15. By all which God is certainly offended, Chriſtian Charity much viola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, the Churches Peace diſturbed, its Enemies moſt gratified, Chriſtianity it ſelf reproached, Irreligion and Ungodlineſs en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged. <hi>Conſtantine</hi> obſerved, That the ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the <hi>Donatiſts</hi> made thoſe that leaſt zeal'd Religion, to deride and ſcoff at it. <hi>Optatus</hi> notes,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Euſebius</hi> Eccl. Hiſt. <hi>l.</hi> 10.</note> That whilſt the <hi>Donatiſts</hi> made a breach in the Church about matters of Diſcipline, and contended that their Separation was lawful, and the Orthodox Church decry'd it as unlawful, the common people were at a ſtand about the practice of Religion, <hi>inter veſtrum licet, &amp; noſtrum non licet, nutant &amp; remigrant a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimae populorum:</hi> And one way in particular, whereby it is very apt to promote Profaneneſs and Irreligion, is by rendering Church-cenſures, and particularly Excommunication, ineffectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al on Offenders. What care they for being excluded the Society of Chriſtians, as long as ſo many reputed religious, do upon the very account of Religion voluntarily exclude themſelves?</p>
               <p n="2">2. The endangering the Safety and Intereſt of the Kingdom: Church-diviſions have brought moſt dreadful Ruines on King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms and Countries. He that reads the Hiſtory of the Turks and Eaſtern Empire, ſhall find that the Chriſtians State-diviſions which were founded on their Church-diviſions, lay'd the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation whereon the Turks erected their Dominions in thoſe places; which was the rooting out of their publick Chriſtian Profeſſion. And <hi>Joſephus</hi> relates, That the Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> and the Jewiſh Nation,<note place="margin">Prol. de Bel. Jud.</note> expoſed them to the deſolation brought upon them by the <hi>Romans.</hi> Such is the evil of Church-diviſions, that <hi>Dion. Alex.</hi> ſaid, That to ſuffer Martyrdom, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Euſeb.</hi> Hiſt. Eccl. <hi>l.</hi> 6.</note> rather than to divide the Church by Schiſms, is not leſs glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious than to be a Martyr for refuſing to offer Sacrifice to Idols.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:47902:22"/>3. A third evil of the preſent Church-diviſions is, the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clining of the regular and publick exerciſe of their Miniſterial Functions, which the ancient Chriſtians ſhew'd ſuch diſlike of, that if any Biſhop, Preſbyter, or Deacon, being ordained, did not undertake his Miniſtration,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Con. Ant.</hi> c. 17.</note> he was to be ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated from all Chriſtian Society, and to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned with the ſame ſeverity as he who undertook the place and minded it not: which regular and publick Miniſtration no Nonconformiſt can in Reaſon or Religion pretend to, ſo long as it is in ſuch manifeſt contempt of lawful Authority as the Holy Scriptures condemn for heinous ſin; much leſs can they pretend to it, that have wholly laid aſide their Miniſtration or Exerciſe of their Miniſtry, as is the caſe of many Nonconformiſts that I could name.</p>
               <p>Were the Pleader employed in this matter (I doubt not) he would produce an Induction of a hundred ſuch particulars, ſhewing the great evil and ſinfulneſs, the pernicious duct and tendency of the preſent Separation. Yet this beloved Separa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion muſt be kept up, though on no other grounds than that on which the late Civil War was raiſed, <hi>(viz.)</hi> pretence to Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation and purity of Religion; like the Papiſts Oath of Secre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy for carrying on the preſent Plot, which though every word of it almoſt be Blaſphemy or Treaſon,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Bolron</hi>'s Narrative.</note> yet is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led a good and pious Deſigne. Whereas if they had the liberty of reforming, what were the Reformation but meer Tinkery, mending one hole and making two? as it was with them in Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi>'s time; there were four Claſſes that had ſet up themſelves in this Kingdom, who addreſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to the Lord <hi>Burleigh</hi> for alteration of the Liturgy;<note place="margin">Dr. <hi>Ham.</hi> view of the Direct. <hi>p.</hi> 2.</note> they had granted them the liberty of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming, and making a new one, ſomewhat ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the <hi>Geneva</hi> form; but this the ſecond Claſſis diſliked, and altered in 600 particulars. That again had the fate to be quarrel'd at by the third Claſſis, and almoſt as many faults found with it as the firſt; and the third was in like manner quarrell'd at by the fourth. So that at laſt the diſſenting of thoſe Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:47902:22"/>
like the diviſion of Tongues at <hi>Babel,</hi> kept the Tower from advancing any higher.</p>
               <p>I would now conclude with my humble requeſt to Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> That he would forbear any further vilifying of Miniſters, railing at Biſhops, and ſcribling againſt Ceremonies, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as that which hath contributed very far to the great danger we are in of ruine both to Church and Kingdom: But I know 'tis as good forbid his Beard to grow. I ſhall end therefore as I began, with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minding him of his own words in <hi>Saints Rest,</hi> Epiſt. Dedic. to the People of <hi>Kedarminſter,</hi> p. 8, 9. <hi>If I ſhould zealouſly preſs my Judgment on others, and ſeek to make a Party for it,</hi> [as he hath done] <hi>and diſturb the Peace of the Church, and ſeparate from my Brethren,</hi> [as he doth] <hi>I ſhould fear lest I ſhould prove a Fire-brand in Hell,</hi> [which God forbid] <hi>for being ſuch a Fire-brand in the Church</hi> [as he is.] <hi>I charge you there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if God ſhould give me up to any factious Church rending courſe,</hi> [as he hath] <hi>that you follow me not a ſtep,</hi> [as you do.] Amen, Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <head>ADVERTISEMENT.</head>
            <p>☞ Some ſeaſonable Advice to all Proteſtant People of <hi>England,</hi> heartily recommended by a Lover of his Country. <hi>Printed for</hi> Randal Taylor. <hi>1681.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
